[Music]
howdy hey any secrets you want to tell
us oh that got me two and a half years
in prison I should probably keep my
mouth
[Music]
shut
what's life like as a spy oh Jared it
was so much fun I miss it very much
actually got to see the world 65
countries recruited nine spies over the
years to work for us it was fun well
let's get this part of the story out of
the way you were actually my high school
teacher I was indeed I was American
government and American history I do
remember you because every once in a
while there's a teacher who stands out
who actually for some reason or another
gets you to pay attention to listen so
thank you for that thank you that's very
kind of you it's insane man this is a
pretty weird world to go from high
school teacher to International Spy you
know Jared life takes these very odd
twists and turns you just never know
what's in store for
[Music]
you that last semester that I had you in
class I went to see the professor and he
said listen I ought to tell you I'm not
really a professor here I'm actually
undercover as a professor I'm a senior
Cia officer would you be interested in
joining the
CIA and I said sure hadn't really
thought of it but I was getting married
soon after graduation I had no job and I
thought well this sounds like fun so
next thing I know a few months later I
was in the
CIA when I first arrived somebody met me
at the front gate and they took me into
an auditorium with about 30 other people
and I raised my right hand and I swore
to uphold the Constitution I didn't
swear to to you know keep the agency's
uh crimes a secret but I swear to uphold
the Constitution and and I meant it and
they put me to work on Iraq and they
said the reason I was being assigned to
Iraq was that nothing ever happened
there so I had been there about 9 months
and just as I begin to feel like I
really know what I'm talking about Iraq
invades Kuwait so next thing I know I'm
I'm going to the White House and
briefing the president and taking a call
at my desk from Colin Powell when he was
the National Security adviser and then I
went went into Kuwait City with the
Marines on Liberation day March 1st
1991 I went through the whole
traditional clandestine operations
training guns explosives
counterterrorism driving jumping out of
an airplane swimming through a swamp to
you know make a dead drop on an island
you're all covered with leeches you have
to fight the cotton mouths that are
swimming across the the bog it it was it
was rough but one thing that I was
really really good at was convincing
people to commit
treason now often times they'll want
money but a lot of times it's not about
the money they want their children to go
to an American University one guy wanted
a new vesa I mean he was willing to
commit treason for me Espionage in
exchange for a vesa one guy did it just
because he loved the United States so
what happened after that in the the
summer of 2000 there was an attempt on
my life in Athens there was a terrorist
group there they planned to kill me on
the way to work one day but they saw
that I was in an armored car and they
knew from earlier surveillance that I
was carrying a weapon and so instead
they killed my nextd door neighbor
Steven Saunders who was the British
defense
atache so I was deemed to be a little
bit too hot meaning too many um of our
enemies knew my true identity and so I
was pulled back from the Middle East and
then September 11th
[Applause]
hit it was in Pakistan as the chief of
counterterrorism operations that I led
what became the biggest counterterrorism
raid in cia's history we captured Abu
zua who we believed at the time was the
number three in al-Qaeda we picked him
up and we threw him into the back of a
filthy Toyota pickup truck
and then he went to what ended up being
the first CIA secret
prison where is he now he's in
Guantanamo now he's been in CIA custody
for almost 14 years now he's not been
charged with a crime I'll add what are
they waiting
for they can't legally charge him with a
crime because everything that he ever
told the CIA was as a result of
torture
they began with the most entry level of
the torture techniques they would grab
him by the lapels and shove them up
against a plywood wall and all that
stuff is humiliating but it's not
painful in any way but then things get
very serious very quickly after that
abuaba for example had an irrational
fear of cockroaches and so they would
keep him in a dog cage and they would
fill the cage with cockroaches just to
make him insane they ended up
waterboarding him 83 times and even
after 83 times uh he gave up no
actionable intelligence he saved no
American lives he disrupted no attacks
against the United States the torture
just simply doesn't
work and so it was it was a crime with
no outcome that you can show the
American people actually helped anybody
there were techniques too Jared that I
that I thought were worse than water
boarding there was something called the
cold cell where we strip a prisoner
naked you chain him to an eyebolt in the
ceiling so his arms are up and he can't
get comfortable he can't kneel or sit or
lay down his cell is chilled to 50° and
every hour somebody goes in and throws
ice water on them that's illegal okay we
killed three people using that technique
but no one was ever charged with a crime
I mean the investigation found that H
yep he died well sorry too bad was an
accident we can't lose who we are as
Americans in the name of
counterterrorism you know we have civil
liberties in this country and I want my
September 10th country
back I left the CIA in 2004 I went into
the private sector and I kept my mouth
shut for five and a half years and in
2007 I got a call from Brian Ross at ABC
News
so I went down to the ABC News studio in
Washington Brian Ross flew in from New
York and I said three things in that
interview that utterly changed the
course of the rest of my life I said the
CIA was torturing its prisoners I said
that torture was official US government
policy and I said the policy was
approved by and signed by the president
of the United
States the CIA was very angry with me
for airing the dirty laundry and so they
asked the justice department to uh to
charge me in January of
2012 I was charged with three counts of
Espionage for the ABC news interview now
the the point really was not to find me
guilty the point was to make an example
of me to deter other whistleblowers from
coming forward and the justice
department really has this down to a
science they know that your attorneys
are very expensive I had 11 attorneys
and I was looking at 45 years in prison
I said I'm not doing 45 minutes I'm
going to fight this I don't care what it
costs that's not really what your
defense attorneys want to hear and you
know we got up over a million bucks and
they said look I think we should
investigate the idea of a plea and they
said well what do you want us to offer
them I said tell them I'll do a year and
a day a year and a day would make me
eligible for early release at 10 and 1/2
months so we offered a year and a day
and they came back with three years we
went with two they said 2 and a half and
they said it's our final offer so what
do you do I have five kids at home do
you roll the dice knowing that the
government wins 98.2% of its cases
according to
propublica I couldn't take that chance
so I took the
deal and then uh just a couple of months
later my attorneys drove me up to prison
and dropped me
[Music]
off anything that keeps you up at night
I'm not sure that we can trust our
government everything that the CIA has
told us since 2001 has been a lie and it
doesn't matter who's in the White House
in August of this year
2015 the White House killed 424 people
in August these are these are people
who've never been charged with a crime
they've never faced their accusers in
court they've never had their day to
explain themselves we're just supposed
to take the cia's word for it that that
these are bad people but then we have
these independent voices Human Rights
Watch Amnesty International the
international Committee of the Red Cross
saying wait a minute 90% of these people
are innocent civilians who just happen
to be near the sight of these drone
attacks one of my attorneys is
representing a drone whistle right now
and he told me recently that he was
operating his drone from a basin I think
it was Nevada or New Mexico he's
connected by radio and the guy in
centcom says you see the
target launch and the guy said I can't
launch there's a child next to him and
the guy at sencom said it's not a child
it's a goat and he said man I'm looking
at it it's a child and he told him
launch
but the guy said I couldn't launch that
thing and he didn't well now he's facing
Court Marshal and possibly other charges
including a dishonorable discharge for
refusing to kill a child I mean is is
this really where we want our country to
be have we so turned our backs on civil
liberty since September 11th in the name
of National Security it was a child
where Americans were better than that
and it's not too late to turn this thing
around Ed Snowden opened so many doors
for people around the world to discuss
these issues that courage is just so
rare and so special he risked
everything and because he did it in such
a public fashion the big guns were
pulled out against him and I told him
don't come home I said you won't get a
fair trial in the the eastern district
of Virginia your jury will be made up of
people from the CIA FBI DOD Homeland
Security and every intelligence and
defense contractor in Washington I said
don't come home not until the American
people come to their senses and realize
what a national service you've
provided what's the worst case
scenario the worst case scenario is that
the courts uphold the ability of NSA to
keep spying on American citizens and
that NSA continues to build facilities
like the new one they have in Utah that
has enough storage space to record and
hold every telephone call text message
and email from Every American citizen
for the next 500 years and that the
American people don't
realize what we're losing here in terms
of our civil liberties you know there
there are no demonstrations in the
street and I just don't understand why
that is so the worst case scenario
really is that the American people don't
come to their censes in time to save the
country
[Music]